soft engine radio episode 125
performance engineering with Chris green
stuff this is software engineering radio
the podcast for professional developers
on the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
so welcome listeners to our new episode
on softening radio this time we talk
about performance engineering and
therefore we invited a guest Chris green
staff and I'm pretty happy that he took
the time to discuss the performance
engineering with us so Chris would you
like to introduce yourself sure thanks
so I work at IBM where I'm a performance
analyst and a performance engineer and
the last several years I've focused
primarily on IBM's client applications
so specifically same time and Lotus
Notes or some applications that I've
worked on and I started at IBM out of
college and stuck around for about 18
months before leaving for a small
company of about 10 where I I blissfully
spent eight years doing some some great
stuff with some great people and and
then have actually been back at IBM for
I think about the past five years and
you're you're there mostly involved as
performance engineering team lead or was
the focus that I be in there yeah it
it's the performance analyst for Lotus
Notes at the moment so that's it's
definitely a team lead I'm working with
both development customers and the test
organizations to try to drive
performance improvements to to IBM
products not cool okay so I think we
will not go into details of IBM products
really but we're worried about telling
telling our listeners what makes the
application perform well so what what
does performance engineering really
means and what does it mean for the
application
yeah that's that's an interesting
question because of course
one man's well-performing application is
not another man's well-performing
application and so I would I guess I
would answer that question by saying
that it's really important to establish
that up front so so when you know
whenever I'm working with teams we work
to establish concrete performance goals
that are actionable and that we can
track towards and then the discussion
becomes what should where should those
goals be set and you know often that
will those goals will be set from a
competitive analysis or simply from you
know experience rules of thumb that you
know anything you I related should take
less than 200 milliseconds or
long-running operations should give user
feedback that that sort of thing a lot a
lot of heuristics coupled with sometimes
guessing on what on what the performance
goal should be so the the performance
goals are more or less defined
informally or do you have some some kind
of formal right apps for them so as you
might imagine at IBM they're they're
pretty formally defined and part of the
reason I say that's because when I
worked at the small company there I did
a lot of performance work all the
developers did a lot of performance work
but this the the kind of work we did
there was you know more informal so at
IBM we we write into you know basically
we rewrite in ship goals that the
product cannot ship unless it meets a
certain level of performance so they're
they're very crisply defined goals that
that are
many meetings happen to discuss what the
exact numbers should be and those are
defined in terms of let's say response
time at the UI or throughput at the big
back end or yeah that's right typically
we'll first for server applications we
we often will define a something around
transactions so total transactions per
second with an acceptable response time
is sort of our catch-all for for backend
goals
client side goals we focus because the
client side is often a single user we
typically are looking at response time
and things like memory footprint okay
you would say performance engineering
does not only mean response times and
throughput but also memory footprint yes
yeah that's something that our that on
the the server side and the client side
customers are really sensitive to and
can be a challenge depending on what
language and framework you are using it
seems like you have concrete examples in
your mind well you know III think basic
engineering says that more abstractions
more levels of indirection more layers
of framework don't come for free and
[Music]
some applications find themselves
sitting very high on application stacks
and there there are great benefits and
great challenges that come with and
that's actually one of the really
interesting things about working as a
performance engineer is you really have
to understand how all of those layers
interact you have to really understand
the the full system all the way down to
the OS often to really realize
sort of gains an understanding that you
need to and and in my experience
application developers because they're
so high on the stack they often get
siloed into focusing on simply the layer
above them and the layer below them and
and they can't really focus on the the
full stack I'll make sure that the full
stack in your mind do you think about
more at the back back-end let's say j2ee
stacks or a huge application servers or
whatever or the client site as well
yeah the client side as well I mean a
lot of the applications that I've worked
on on the client side are built atop
Eclipse so you know you at a simple
level you have the JVM then you have
Eclipse and OSGi on top of that and
often there will be other proprietary
code on top of that and then your
application code so even in a situation
on the client it's it's not hard before
you're you're sitting on a pretty tall
stack okay I think we should come back
to this OSGi and Eclipse platform on the
client side later on sounds pretty
interesting um before we we we move
forward who defines the the performance
goals so we talked a lot about which
performance goals to define and how do
you find them but but who defines them
in your case sounds like huge long
meetings who defines it at Indiana yeah
it's it's an interesting negotiation
between the performance team the
development team and the sales and
marketing team and there are a lot of
interests you know ultimately everyone
is trying to create the product that our
customers are going to like and that
they're going to want to buy
so typically meetings involved with
those three parties you you try to
negotiate what you think you can do to
meet customer goals or exceed customer
goals and expectations
and at the same time not have a
spiraling out of control development
budget and it's really a trade off like
like all engineering decisions do you
have any any any kind of ratio how how
much time do you spend doing the the
development of the project for
performance engineering know it for
every release of a product that I've
worked on it's varied a lot and I you
know I should also say that I sort of
have the privilege working here in that
I work I really work as a consultant to
development so that that means I'm
profiling code I'm making code changes
and I'm reviewing code changes at the
same time that the majority of the
developers are adding features fixing
bugs unit testing the normal sort of
development tasks so in other words iBM
is large enough that that really you can
have two teams focusing like that and
when I worked for the small company that
obviously wasn't the case you you would
each individual would split their time
between doing some development some
performance do you have some some kind
of feeling what what is it good let's
say good good budget or good percentage
of the work of the whole team let's say
developing a project how much time to
spend for performance engineering or how
much time is necessary I don't the way I
would approach that question is going
back to upfront stating the goals right
because once and it's important to say
that performance in and of itself has no
value except to reach the goals that
you've established right because you can
you cannot you can spend forever
improving any given code path or
improving your memory footprint but
there there's definitely a diminishing
return and and one of the ways that you
you handle that is by establishing goals
upfront and once those goals are reached
then you don't work on those those areas
and
so a lot of it I would say comes down to
how aggressive you make the goals okay
and that that might depend on the kind
of product you're developing right
exactly if maybe if you develop a
database you might have s much more time
optimizing the performance than
developer a business banking application
UI stuff yeah and and you know another
another really common example is version
1 of your product has shipped customers
like it but they're complaining about
performance so version 2 performance is
now a bigger issue and and it gets a lot
more attention yeah good point I think
we will come back to the point when -
you went to optimize performance end end
I think that the next logical question
would be how do you find performance
bottlenecks and problems so maybe which
tools are using or i/o using tools or
are you doing something else yeah so we
we've talked some about about goals the
the next most important well the the
next very important part after goals are
having measurements you know I like to
say that you you can't improve what you
you can't measure okay and so III bring
that up because it plays into the tools
the the you you have to have solid
measurements and ideally repeatable
measurements with historical data to
really move the ball forward in terms of
improving the performance so we split it
up into measurements the and then
analysis so the measurements tell you
where you are relative to your goals and
then the analysis is responsible for
telling you how to improve that how to
get closer to your goals or exceed your
goals how do you do that the measurement
so measurement
is very important and very messy it it's
not a it's not terribly sexy it's it's a
lot of work and especially as our
product is in development it's very
challenging to keep your your your
measurement scripts in parity with what
the with how the product is changing so
some of the tools that we use to do
measurements are loadrunner
which you may have heard of it's a
that's really to test web based
applications
so it's jmeter is is an Apache project
that's that's similar and what tools
like Lode Runner or jmeter do are more
or less screen scrape your application
and then let you parameterize that
screen scraping so that you can you can
substitute virtual users for for real
users and you use those tools to
basically apply load to the application
under test and then just as important as
applying the load you you then have to
have performance metrics gathered as
that load is applied because again you
what you're really trying to do is
you're trying to you're trying to figure
out at what point the load on the server
becomes so great that the response time
exceeds the goals that you established I
mean this is especially important for
for web applications the goal isn't
really to knock the the server over the
goal is to understand how
end-user response time varies as you
apply more load sounds like your you've
completely automated this kind of
creating load and and gathering those
metrics um I
ideally automation with with constant
validation it's it's really challenging
like I said as a as a product as a
product is being developed the UI
changes of course and you have to be
very careful that your automation
scripts are doing the same thing that a
real user would be doing not to mention
that it's difficult to keep that
automation in sync so not only do you
have to worry that it's doing the right
thing from build to build it it
typically will break and you have to go
back and and figure out what changed and
fix it it's it's a lot of work which is
which is frankly why a lot of a lot of
people prefer to skip that step there's
a point at which you get diminishing
returns
so one of the one of the things that we
try to do when we're establishing goals
and when we're coming up with these
measurements and these scripts is making
sure that we we hit the parts of the
application that we think most of our
customers will hit with them as
frequency because the complexity of a
lot of applications today make it very
difficult to automate the entire thing
that said that's what I'm describing
right now was really it's almost a an
external view of your application to the
the the the other side of that are
having developers through unit tests or
through performance unit tests look at
application performance from from
point of view also okay so you can come
out up from different from different
angles the but but a real important
point to make there that that we see
time and again is especially for web
applications and really for client
applications to an element that is often
missed in doing performing unit tests or
having developers do their own
performance testing is the huge impact
that a well-populated database or a
well-populated
set of data has on those performance
tests in other words it's not uncommon
to have developers come to you and say
my set of functionality performs great
and you start asking more questions and
you realize that you know it was run
against a database with ten users
whereas our customers run it with
thousands of users and they see very
different very different behavior so one
of the one of the big challenges but in
addition to measurements are having
valid populations of data and that's
really you know again it's not it's not
sexy work but it's it's really crucial
to having a well-populated data to get
remotely reasonable results from from
your performance measurements and and
you know you can't really improve
performance if you aren't measuring what
what your customers are really going to
see okay so it's it's somehow on the on
the same level that you say your test
setting should be as closely related to
the real user setting as possible right
so having the same differences you you
emulate the same amount of users having
the the same size of data in the
database and the same kind of load that
thousands of users would create in
reality for your performance testing
that's right yeah and and as you can
imagine that sounds like a lot of work
and for for complicated web apps it's a
great deal of work but but you know I
mean a funny funny example of this are
simple things like and I see this on the
client as well like pagination right if
the web app is giving is serving back a
screen that doesn't have any pagination
and that works well when you have less
than 30 less than 50 elements coming
back but as soon as you start returning
hundreds or thousands then the end user
experience the both the server load and
the browser user experience suffer
significantly in the in the same way
that if you think of something like a
mail client and if you have 2,000 or
3,000 messages in your inbox you
shouldn't have to pay the cost to touch
all 2 or 3,000 messages to simply view
the first page of your of your inbox and
those sorts of pagination issues come up
time and time again because typically
because developers are testing with a
small set of data so so data population
is really big you you said that to find
the performance bottlenecks and to see
where you are therefore the the
measurements are are important so do you
think that you you think that you first
need to have some solid measurements and
then you optimize performance not the
other way around
so having this this kind of first make
it run and then make it fast yeah I
think it's gonna I think it'll depend a
lot on the the size of the organization
the size of the team I mean obviously if
someone you know comes to you and says
it takes me four minutes to log in I
would say it's a it's actually very
similar to how I've tried to introduce
unit testing into organizations that
aren't doing unit testing it it's rarely
beneficial to boil the ocean and say you
need to add unit tests for all your
major functions instead I would say well
the next defect that you get in that
that that comes in try to write a unit
test for that fix it and then accumulate
a set of unit tests as you go forward
and I I would say the same applies for
performance testing so in the example
where it takes a long time to log in
ideally you would write a measurement
for that or a performance unit test for
that then you would fix the problem and
now you have your you're accumulating a
suite of measurements or performing unit
tests so that that doesn't regress in
future builds okay so during the
performance measurements and
optimization step by step yeah and and
you know it it really will vary on on
the the organization as to to how you
can do that as I said I'm sort of
privileged to be able to approach
performance in the way that I do here
I'm glad that I worked at a small
company where that they simply couldn't
do some of the things that that we can
afford to do here in terms of
performance so you already gave one
example of a typical performance problem
having this huge data and this paging or
pagination can you can give us a brief
introduction or or an overview or for
water whether that what are the typical
performance problems that you observe in
an applications on the server side as
well as on the client side let's see
I'll start with the client-side because
that's where I've been spending more of
my time recently startup is an
interesting one because at some level
you would say startup isn't that
important because a lot of people don't
start up more than once a week or
sometimes even a month because they
suspend their machines or they they
simply don't start up that frequently
but the reality is a lot of customers
have have come back and said that
startup is very important to them for
whatever reason and so startup is as an
area that that I've been focusing on a
lot this this year really and that
that's a challenge any Java based or
eclipse based application has challenges
and in start-up so that's a that's a
typical one you know memory footprint is
is another typical one Java applications
in particular and this is true on the
client and the server you know have lots
of repetitive strings and memory with
with the amount of XML parsing and XML
that that goes on and a lot of java
application servers you have lots of
memory dedicated to two strings on the
client side I another big area are our
resource leaks and I'm specifically here
again talking about Eclipse based
applications where SWT is SWT requires
you to manage your own UI resources
basically you can't you can't rely on
the the Java garbage collector there
like you can in swing and you know then
just the obvious ones of doing doing too
much work in the UI thread doing too
much io is another another area that
that we see especially with with cold
startup do you observe often algorithmic
performance problems there
certainly algorithmic problems that come
up there they're usually in my
experience anyway they're they're
usually great fun to find because a lot
of which I should have actually started
by saying that you know the the first
thing you have to do is determine
whether or not your your CPU constrained
or i/o constrained and typically and if
your algorithm is the problem you'll see
that as a a CPU problem and often those
problems the reason I said they're fun
to find is because they're often easier
to fix then there's some other problems
that I run into because the profilers
will typically produce profilers excel
at finding CPU bottlenecks and typically
once you find those there in my
experience not not too bad to fix some
some or some of those that come to minor
I'll occasionally see people using a
list when they should be using a map
they're they're basically scanning the
list looking for an item instead of
using a constant time map is a simple
example
oh yeah but but but it also is it's also
related to your to the thing you
mentioned earlier about the the size of
your data right because if you have just
yeah absolutely just ten items in your
database it doesn't matter if you have a
scanner list or if you use it is use a
map but if you have millions of items in
your list and if a real real sized data
volume then then you can observe those
problems right yes that's right as a
simple order analysis shows that for for
a lot of VMs under a hundred items um
you can get away with a list and in some
cases it's even faster
so you're right that I mean that that
definitely feeds back into the the the
population issue so one of the one of
the ways that we try to approach that is
take take our systems that are fully
populated and do the profiling of a
single user on that system that's one
approach and another approach is when
you're looking at concurrency problems
typically a single user isn't going to
show you much it's not impossible to
deadlock with a single user but it's
it's usually find that pretty fast so
there's some bigger there's a bigger
challenge when you're trying to profile
an application that's under load because
most profilers skew and create enough
overhead that you you can't do that
under load and so you you have to fall
back to often simpler tools so yeah debt
population plays placed directly into
the profiling and analysis so this is
more or less the the algorithmic side
and then some kind of low-level stuff
you talked before about the layers in in
applications and these huge technology
sticks that we use today so what do you
think how how important is the an imino
architecture of the application for your
performance goals and for the
performance problems it's hugely
important and I should mention that that
that is so something something else that
that we do here is the performance
analyst attend all of the architect and
design meetings to have to bring the
performance voice to the table
because you know as is often said the
earlier you you fix the problem or in
this case even the the earlier that you
don't write code that that isn't going
to perform or scale the better but then
to your point that there's a lot of
there's a lot of challenge in building
applications that sit on on so many
layers the the the best that I can
probably say there is that you really
need to understand how the layers below
you interact oh s GI and Eclipse based
applications are a good example you you
really have to understand how bundles
are activated and really try to embrace
eclipses model of delaying activation as
long as possible it's it's unfortunately
too easy to to violate that you know
that possibly better better tooling or
better education might might help with
that but it's it's a real challenge when
you when you're sitting so high up on
the stack did you observe performance
problems there that were very very
difficult to solve because you need to
change the architecture fundamentally
maybe or change may be important parts
of the architecture to solve those
performance problems yes yes definitely
I'm trying to think of a good example
I mean OSGi it was around I think it was
the move from eclipse to to eclipse 308
well at the time Eclipse stored as I was
saying a lot of XML in memory and it was
very redundant and one of the changes
that was made was basically to cache
more of that and use indexes use
integers under the covers to represent
the same information that you were
pulling from your your plugin XML
that's an example of an architectural
change that was made in Eclipse to
address some of the sorts of things I'm
talking about I wasn't specifically
involved in that one but it sounds like
this performance optimization was done
inside the single layer of the
architecture let's say the whatever
extension registry of Eclipse and does
not affect the whole application that's
right
so did you also observe those
performance problems where you need to
change let's say vertically your your
application from from the base layers to
the to the top layers yeah that that
definitely happened the
startup is actually a good example
startup is one of those problems where
when you when you profile startup
typically know one thing stands out I
mean there's no obvious hot spot okay
startup tends to be spread across the
entire infrastructure so it's I like to
call it the death of a thousand cuts
because it very you take lots of very
small things and add them up and then
you get startup problems so for
something for something like that
they're you know they're there were no
sir
Silver Bullet so obviously it was
minimizing or reducing the number of
bundles that are activated so in the
last version of the product that I
worked on we basically cut that in half
and when you when you look at any
individual bundle and you try to go to
development and say you need to take
this out of the startup path you'll
often get pushed back because what that
one bundle contributes to startup is
minimal it's only when you take them in
the hole that that you can really see
the the full impact which is sort of
contrary to most performance advice of
the 80/20 rule or focus on the the hot
spots and and
so startup doesn't doesn't really play
as well with without advice but if I
think about my activities and
performance optimizing or doing
performance engineering stuff in my
projects I think I've observed nearly
the same so that they're sometimes
they're the problems where I can I use a
profiler and you find one hot spot and
say okay this operation takes long
because they're scanning a list instead
of using a map or whatever and it's easy
to solve
some some kind of low-hanging fruit
mm-hm and sometimes it's just some of
thousands of small operations which you
cannot really avoid and all those
operations are fast and only only adding
them up and doing all all of them at
once causes a phone's problem so you
would say that having this kind of
performance problems they're they're
harder to solve and one idea is to let's
say move a lot of those operations to a
later point in time so having them done
lazily after other operations so they
get a get better feedback or faster
feedback yeah well exactly and I mean
another another good example in an
eclipse is the Eclipse did a nice job of
separating the code that needs to be run
from text that needs to be displayed to
users and by that I mean Eclipse can
show me the shell of a view and that you
can have an icon and that view can have
a title and from an end users
perspective I think that that view
exists that it's real that you know I
can do something with it but the reality
is the code behind that view likely
hasn't been loaded unless I've used it
already and so that's a that's a nice
way to defer all the loading of that
code that that's behind that view and
you you know it was architected that way
you you that's the sort of thing that
it's hard to change after the fact right
because most people would just write
their Java class and
they wouldn't have the Java class
returned an icon and it would return the
the label or the text to show the user
but as soon as you've done that you now
have to let that class and in any
classes that it depends on so it would
be difficult it's difficult to go from
that to the this the separation that
Eclipse made from the beginning and that
those are architectural changes that are
very hard to to force them do you think
similar problems also possible on the
backend site so having let's say a
transaction doing thousands of Chinese
steps and causing a performance problem
because so many small fast operations
they need to be done and if so do you
have any ideas or any typical patterns
how to solve those kind of problems
because in those cases for me it sounds
like it's not always possible to say
okay I defer some of those operations
Chile in a point in time right yeah I
mean for the for the backend you know
again it's gonna depend a lot on where
your bottleneck is for a lot of the
applications that I've worked on on the
backend the bottleneck ends up being the
database in cases like that you really
have to go to the database and ask it
why these particular transactions or
these queries are are taking so long
right and databases are generally very
good at telling you why it's taking a
long time they don't need help in
telling you how you can make it not but
they at least can can show you the
access plan and show you why it's taking
a long time to return a query and then
with that information you have to you
know often decide to restructure or add
indexes change the query pull it you
know denormalize I mean they're there
there are a lot of ways that that you
can that you can attack a problem like
that but again it has to go back to
first knowing that that's where you
should look and
the way the way you do that is by
monitoring the the application server
the database server LDAP whatever
servers you have while they're under
load and the measurements will tell you
where those bottlenecks are and then you
have to just go to each one but but
having you mentioned the D normalization
or restructuring of data or schemas or
whatever that brings me to two to the
next question do you observe typical
let's say situations where you need to
do a trade off between nice modular and
clean design of your application or data
structure whatever M and performance
goals so we say okay hmm this this will
be a nice design but or a nice
architecture but we have to to to break
it somehow and make it uglier too to
meet the performance goals yes database
D normalization is probably the one of
the examples that that comes to mind
there III would I guess I would say that
the the flipside of that is well written
code well factored code is also easier
to make performance improvements to you
know I guess simpler is better write
less code is easier to improve then then
more code so they don't always oppose
each other but they often do adding
another simple example is just the is
concurrency having to add concurrency to
your application unless you have the
benefit of using some message oriented
concurrency if you're in Java using
monitors and Java constructs for
concurrency it it often takes a simple
application and makes it much more
complicated what do you say that a good
architecture and a good design makes the
system perform well or would you say a
good
and flexible architecture makes it
easier to improve the performance that's
a good question i I I can think of
examples where that was true and then I
can think of lots of examples where it
wasn't yeah I mean III keep going back
you can tell that I've I've suffered in
the past but I keep going back to being
layer number 11 on a ten deep layered
architecture you're here opportunities
to improve performance when you're that
far above the the stack are challenging
on the other hand I've actually seen
products that were in a situation like
that where they were they were much
higher up on the stack in version one of
their product they got beat up in the
market for it and in version two of the
product they basically got rid of
several layers beneath them and you know
maybe wrote directly to the the servlet
API instead of some of the the layers
that were between them before and that's
a lot of work and a lot of a lot of
products can't afford to do that but
sometimes that's the right thing to do
but it sounds like you you would vote
for simpler architectures and and fewer
layers instead of making it all
extremely complex and huge absolutely
okay yeah that's that's my impression as
well so having a having less lacks
technology and less layers and less
abstractions sometimes better than doing
this kind of over abstracting everything
yeah I think it's interesting having
been in the Java space for a while and
seeing you know what's going on on the
server side and the complexity there and
how frameworks have sprung up that are
much simpler that take a lot of the
market share from the the the large
application layers it's it's interesting
too
to see that resonate right that simple
is better it's interesting to see how
Java as an industry is is moving and
trying to adapt you talked about
threading in the threading or
concurrency could make an application a
lot more complex
I would agree to that completely but do
you think that um threading can be
useful to improve performance if I think
about the UI thread and having a
responsive UI that you defer stuff to a
background thread instead doing it in
the UI thread for example oh yeah no
it's it's absolutely essential
there are many horror stories of you
clicking something in the UI and going
off to a database and spending 10 or 20
seconds because your network connection
is down before the UI is you know is
released and the end user can use it the
those sorts of things happen a lot and
there unfortunately
extremely easy to do it's a it's a
constant effort to to not have long
running operations block the UI thread
and so it's yeah I would say it's
essential that you that you understand
and use what your your platform provides
provides to you I mean with that said I
all again use the example of Eclipse
Eclipse has a jobs framework which is
basically threading it's a thin layer
that that uses threads under the covers
and uses a pool of threads and so if
you're writing eclipse based
applications or rich client applications
on Eclipse and that's what you you
should definitely use but I've also seen
people go too far so a good example is
if you imagined male client and you open
your inbox and let's say
you want to do some long running
operation for each of the users you may
want to get there you know whether
they're online or not there's their
status I've seen people before create a
job for to do that which is the right
thing to do but unfortunately they
created a job for every person in the
inbox which isn't the right thing to do
because you'll basically blow your
thread pool and you'll create a thread
then for every single person in your
inbox which which is a bad idea if you
have many emails so you have to you
definitely have to be aware of what your
your underlying framework is providing
to you and use it appropriately but you
would say such such a thin layer like
the eclipse jobs API or similar stuff is
useful instead of programming the
threads and monitors by hand yes
absolutely I mean even before eclipse
did their jobs framework I was a big
user a big fan of Doug Leah's
concurrency utils oh yeah very good
example yeah which I guess go all the
way back to one fours I think where they
were first introduced so yeah I'm a big
fan of his work and try to try to get
people to use that instead of using the
the primitive monitor synchronization
that that Java provides out of the box
but sometimes you have to yeah but but I
I observed in projects that you
sometimes it's it's just pure hell to
say put a long-running operations and
the breakdown background using these
low-level operations and having the
swing thread and you cannot change the
model whatever without getting really
really strange behavior at the UI yes
because you changed the model in a
different thread and stuff like that so
yeah sounds like some made some API in
some very very maybe thin layer
above that is very useful yes yeah we'd
agree um so we are now close to the end
of the episode so um I would like to ask
you some the typical question at the end
any any additional words of wisdom you
would like to share with our listeners I
guess it would really just be a recap in
my opinion the key to up to performance
is having clearly defined goals a good
automation and good scripts that you can
use to drive load and exit you know and
then basically as you execute those
goals you're collecting the performance
metrics of each of the machines and it's
a it's important to then store that
information historically and then with
that information you then have a good
basis for how to make improvements and
what areas need improving and once you
have that then you then you pull out
your profilers then you pull out your
network analyzer tools and you dig into
to fixing those problems but until you
can measure it it's difficult to to
improve it or if you do improve it you
don't have much guarantee that the next
build it won't regress and you won't
notice because you aren't measuring it
yeah
good summary of the episode I think we
could dive into much more detail about
how do we exactly analyze those problems
but there might be a topic for another
episode so I would like to thank you
very very much for taking the time
talking with us about performance
engineering and thank you thank you very
much you're welcome I'm a big fan of the
show thanks
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
solve the engineering radio soft
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website and s/ii -
radio dot length if you want to support
us you can donate to the AC radio team
via the website or you can advertise for
su radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team at s e - radio net or if
it is specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of SU radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under
Creative Commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the quad State Music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle
[Music]